Bruce Lancaster Papers
Bruce Lancaster Papers
1931-1964
Lancaster, Bruce, 1896-1963.
9.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, novelist. Lancaster wrote historical novels. Collection includes book manuscripts, research notes, articles, speeches; a small amount of correspondence; and a photograph.
149119
Biographical History
Bruce Lancaster was born in Worcester, Massachusetts on August 22, 1896. He served in the U.S. Army along the Mexican border in 1916 and later in France. After the war he returned to school and received a B.A. from Harvard in 1918. He worked in administration and sales for nine years, after which he served in the U.S. Foreign Service as Vice-Consul to Kobe, Japan (1928-1932). Following his return to the United States he became assistant secretary to the board of governors of the Society of New York Hospitals, and began to write the novels which would make him famous. Most of his works are historical novels, including Guns of Burgoyne, Trumpet to Arms, and Blind Journey. He has also written historical non-fiction, such as From Lexington to Liberty (1955).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Bruce Lancaster Papers are divided into five series. Correspondence (1931, 1952, 1960) consists of a very small amount of incoming correspondence and correspondence of others. Subject files (undated) comprises research material, notes, and a galley proof. Manuscripts (1939-1958) contains manuscript versions of articles, books, speeches, and a paper. Published material (1939-1964) consists of an article and several books. Scrapbooks consist of two volumes containing clippings, reviews, and other material relating to Lancaster's books.
Arrangement of the Collection
Boxes 1-9 appear to be unprocessed and remain in the order originally received. Boxes 10-18 have been processed and material is in alphabetical order by type. When published books were removed for separate cataloging, boxes 14 through 17 were combined into a single box labelled "Box 14-17."
Separated Material
A number of published books by Lancaster were removed from the collection for separate cataloging. Please refer to and search for "Lancaster, Bruce" as author to located these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Lancaster, Bruce, 1896-1963 Archives.; Authors, American.; Novelists, American.; Popular literature, United States.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Authors.; Novelists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Lancaster, 1965-67.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Incoming: A, D, T (Box 10)
  - Correspondence of others (Box 10)
- Subject files
  - Clippings (Box 3)
  - Galley proof of book Ticonderoga (Box 10)
  - Japan (Box 10)
  - Notes (Box 10)
  - Research material
    - Revolutionary War (Box 10)
    - 1838-1842 (Box 10)
    - Civil War (Box 10)
    - Blind Journey, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Bright to the Wanderer (Box 11)
    - Fort Ticonderoga (Box 11)
    - Phantom Fortress (Box 11)
- Manuscripts
  - Books
    - Big Knives
      - Galleys, dust jacket (Box 6)
      - Typescript (Box 2)
      - Typescript (Box 18)
    - Blind Journey, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Bride of a Thousand Cedars
      - Holograph manuscript (Box 3)
      - Typescript, 2 folders (Box 11, 12)
    - Bright to the Wanderer, typescript with corrections (Box 5)
    - For Us the Living, typescript (Box 1)
    - From Lexington to Liberty, galleys (Box 4)
    - Letter Book of Christian Febinger 1779-1780 (Box 12)
    - Letter Book 1780-1782, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Letter Book and Orderly Book 1777-1786 (Box 12)
    - Night March, typescript (Box 7)
    - Orderly Book 1778 (Box 12)
    - Orderly Book 1781-1782 (Box 12)
    - Phantom Fortress, typescript with corrections (Box 9)
    - Trumpet to Arms, galleys (Box 4)
    - Venture in the East, typescript with corrections (Box 8)
  - Papers
    - "General John Glover" (Box 13)
  - Speeches
    - Complete (Box 13)
    - Incomplete (Box 13)
    - Fragments (Box 13)
- Published material
  - Articles by
    - "Writing a Lincoln Novel," Abraham Lincoln Quarterly, vol. 2 no. 8, Dec 1943 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
  - Books
    When published books were removed for separate cataloging, boxes 14 through 17 were combined into a single box labelled "Box 14-17."
    - The Blind Journey, extra copy, hardcover and paperback (Box 14-17)
    - Hojt Spil (Danish, No Bugles Tonight) (Box 14-17)
    - L'Insigne Scarlate (French, The Scarlet Patch) (Box 4)
    - Phantom Fortress (Box 1)
    - Trumpet to Arms (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  - Wide Sleeve and Bride of 1000 Cedars (Box 18)
  - Guns of Burgoyne (Volume 1)